Guide to the David L. Rosenhan Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
David L. Rosenhan papers
circa 1970-1990
SC1116
Rosenhan, David L., 1929-2012.
12 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
David L. Rosenhan (1929 – February 6, 2012) was a psychologist and pioneer in the application of psychological methods to the practice of trial law process, including jury selection and jury consultation. Rosenhan was the author of more than 80 books and research papers, including one of the most widely read studies in the field of psychology, “On Being Sane in Insane Places” (1973). He is best known for the Rosenhan experiment, a study challenging the validity of psychiatry diagnoses.
Born in Jersey City, New Jersey, David L. Rosenhan was a yeshiva student in his youth and received a BA in mathematics (1951) from Yeshiva College, and an MA in economics (1953) and PhD in psychology (1958) from Columbia University
Before joining the Stanford faculty, David Rosenhan was a member of the faculties of Swarthmore College, Princeton University, Haverford College, and University of Pennsylvania. He also served as a research psychologist at Educational Testing Service. He was a psychologist for the Counseling Center at Stevens Institute of Technology from 1954 to 1956; a lecturer at Hunter College and director of research in the Department of Psychiatry at City Hospital at Elmhurst from 1958 to 1960; assistant professor for the Departments of Psychology and Sociology at Haverford College from 1960 to 1962; lecturer for the Department of Psychology and Psychiatry at the University of Pennsylvania from 1961 to 1964; lecturer for the Department of Psychology at Princeton University from 1964 to 1968; and professor in the Department of Psychology and Education at Swarthmore College from 1968 to 1970.
In 1973 Rosenhan published "On Being Sane in Insane Places", one of the most widely read articles in the field of psychology. The article details the Rosenhan experiment. The experiment arranged for eight individuals with no history of psychopathology to attempt admission into twelve psychiatric hospitals during a three-year period. They described hallucinations and “empty” feelings and were diagnosed as paranoid schizophrenics. As soon as they were admitted they began acting normally and waited for the hospital staff to notice. The hospital staff never did notice, although many of the real patients caught on to the fakes. Psychiatrists attempted to treat the individuals using psychiatric medication. All eight were discharged within 7 to 52 days, but only when they had stated that they accepted their diagnosis. In a later part of the study, a research and teaching hospital challenged Rosenhan to run a similar experiment involving its own diagnosis and admission procedures. Psychiatric staff were warned that at least one pseudo-patient might be sent to their institution. 83 out of 193 new patients were believed by at least one staff member to be actors. In fact, Rosenhan sent no actors. The study concluded that existing forms of diagnosis were grossly inaccurate in distinguishing individuals without mental disorders from those with mental disorders. Rosenhan wrote, “It is clear that we cannot distinguish the sane from the insane in psychiatric hospitals. … The consequences to patients hospitalized in such an environment—the powerlessness, depersonalization, segregation, mortification, and self-labeling—seem undoubtedly counter-therapeutic.”. The paper created an explosion of controversy. Critics have questioned the validity and credibility of the study, but concede that the consistency of psychiatric diagnoses needs improvement.
At a time when legal scholars were just beginning to look to economics for insights into legal analysis, Professor Rosenhan was among the first to draw from the social sciences, especially experimental psychology, to examine assumptions made by legal scholars in the trial process. Building on research on juror behavior undertaken by the University of Chicago Law School Jury Project in the 1950s, Professor Rosenhan began to focus on other aspects of juror behavior. Among his interests was the jurors’ ability to abide by the judge’s instructions to disregard evidence the judge had ruled inadmissible.
Along with Martin Seligman, Rosenhan believed that there are seven main features of abnormality: suffering; maladaptiveness; vividness and unconventionality; unpredictability and loss of control; irrationality and incomprehensibility; observer discomfort; and violation of moral and ideal standards.
He was a fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science; a former president of the American Psychological Association; a former director of the American Psychology-Law Society; a former president of the American Board of Forensic Psychology; a former vice-president of the Institute for Psychosocial Interaction; a former director at the Mental Research Institute; member of the Clinical Projects Research Review Committee at the National Institute of Mental Health; visiting fellow at the Centre for Socio-Legal Studies, Wolfson College and Department of Experimental Psychology at Oxford University from 1977 to 1978; visiting professor at University of Western Australia, Tel Aviv University, and Oxford University from 1984-1985; and a visiting professor in the Department of Psychology at Georgetown University in 1988.
He died on February 6, 2012, at the age of 82. He was survived by his son Jack Rosenhan and his granddaughters Cecily and Yael, as well as his brother Hershel.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of Psychology. Faculty.; Stanford University. Department of Psychology.; Stanford University. School of Law.; Community mental health services.; Law--Study and teaching--United States; Psychology--Study and teaching (Graduate) --California --Stanford.; Psychology.
Collection Contents
- Grants
  - Loose Items (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - LANG MH10993-08 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Effectiveness of Individual Psychotherapy (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Windholz (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Expectancy and desensitization in the treatment of fear (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cognitive Control of Anger and Aggression (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Neurophysiologic Correlates of Autistic Behavior (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Janis, Irving (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Factors Influencing Tolerance of Deprivation (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Psychologic, Immunologic and Pharmacological Aspects of Asthma (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Psychologic, Pharmacologic and Immunologic Interactions in Asthma (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Behavioral Treatment Approaches to Schizophrenia (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Function of the Human Potential Movement (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Progress Report appendix (Kanfer, Frederick) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Human Self-Regulation (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Nature of Schizophrenic Thought Disorders (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Aversion and Interpersonal Factors in Smoking Control (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Social Interaction of Deviant Preschool Children (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Comparison of Pre-sleep and "Extrasensory" Stimuli in Dreams (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bootstrapping the Schizoid Taxon with MMPI Patterns (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sleep Disturbance in Depressive Disorders (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Voluntary Control Over Psycho-physiologic Activities (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Information Processing and Schizophrenia (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Treatment of Asthma by Behavioral Desensitization (RG) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clinical Decision Behaviors in Psychiatric Diagnosis (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Assessing and Modifying Social Behavior in a Hospital (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Depression: A Clinical Research Approach (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Psychophysiological Family Research (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Hypertensive Pressures During Psychological Study (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Hyperactive Behavior in Girls (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence to Grant Applications Borrowed By Beverly Rose (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Cognitive Response to Psychological Stress (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sensory Regulation Aspects of Aggressive Behavior (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Modifications of Defenses in Psychoanalysis (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Defective Epinephrine Mobilization in Bronchial Asthma (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Infantile Autism: Methodological Studies of Diagnosis (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Perceptual and Proprioceptive Dysfunction in Schizophrenia (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Feminine Identity in Adolescent Girls (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Factors Influencing Tolerance for Deprivation (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Behaviorial Treatment of Childhood Gender Problems (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Grants 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - MH 24477-01 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Therapeutic efficacy in anxiety syndromes (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Behavior modification in childhood asthma (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Further studies on sleep utterance (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Dependency and deprivation of obesity (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Associative disorder and schizophrenic predisposition (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Therapy methods for the lower class neurotic patient (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Developmental Factors in Schizophrenia (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Genetic Analysis of Schizophrenic Families (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Data Bank to Assess Psychiatric Theory Outcomes (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - A Genetic-Epidemiologic Study of Presenile Dementia (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Studies of Early Infantile Autism and Controls (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Treatment of Asthma through Conditioning (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Assessment of Interpersonal Behavior (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Videotape Feedback in Psychotherapy (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Cognitive Response to Psychological Stress (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Evaluation of Behavior training as a Therapy Approach (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Arousal, Retrieval, and Autism (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Affective Disorders in Children (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Misc, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Grants 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Learned helplessness and depression (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Learned Helplessness and Depression (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Seligman MH19604-04 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Adolescent Behavioral Classification Project (ABCP) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Communication of Symptomatic Complaints (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Social Competence and Behavioral Style in Mental Patients (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Social Competence and Behavior in mental patients (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Mother-Child antecedents to schizophrenic development (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - An Outcome and Process Study of Intensive Therapy (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Pre-Sleep and "Extrasensory" Stimuli in Dreams, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - An Optimum A-B Scale of Psychotherapist Effectiveness (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - An Optimum A-B Scale fo Psychotherapist Effectiveness (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Adjustment of Children of Schizophrenic Parents (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Body Movement Aspects of Personality and Social Role (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Dimensions and Validity of Depression Scales (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Self-Change and Coping in Response to Crisis (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Outcome Variables in Group Psychotherapy (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Psychobehavioral Effects of Sleep Pattern Variation (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Research
  - Loren Chapman, Related to: MH 24797-01 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Small, Joyce G. MH 14638-04 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Rubins, Jack L. MH 19606-01 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Loose items (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Supervised Visitation (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Encoding+Recall; Lawrence, Kavanagh (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Moore, Underwood, Rosenhan (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Seligman-Rosenhan Abnormal Text (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Fusting/Norton (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Abnormal Text Correspondence: Norton Publishers (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - HRW Publications Schedule - Contract List (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Chansky-Freeman (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Ekman (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - SANE Correspondence A-L (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - SANE Correspondence M-Z (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - H.H. Notes (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Norristown Hospital Notes (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Characteristics of Hospitals (folder 1) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Characteristics of Hospitals (folder 2) (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Stanton Wheeler letters (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Obedience Write-Up (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Obedience Sample Typed Protocols (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Obedience Raw Data (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Obediance Experiment Data & Frequency Data (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Obediance Data Graphs and Analysis (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Obediance, Reliability of Ratings of Interviews - credibility (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Obediance, Reliability of Ratings of Interviews (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Obediance SS and Code (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Obediance Interview Ratings - Hipp (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Obediance Data and Analysis (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Obediance Daily Data Sheet (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Obediance Analysis of Interviews Glen White (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Obediance Personality Data (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Obediance and Rebellion (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Contextual Nature of Psychiatric Diagnosis (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Photo of Samcattor (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Madness: In the Eye of the Beholder (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Some Perceptual Correlates of Anxiety (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Haritos-Fatouros (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E-F, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - G, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - H, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - I-J, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - K, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - L, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - M, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - N, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - O, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - P-Q, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ostrom (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - O'Karma, Henry (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Olesen, Virginia (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ongirski-Lehnhoff, Hannelore (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Opton, Edward (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Orne, Martin (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Osborne, J.E. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Osherson, Daniel (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ostrom, Thomas (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Owen, Alan (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Obeso, Kenneth (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clare, Diane (Proseminar, Inc.) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Phelps and Clark (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Paloutzian, Eunice (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pascal, Christopher (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Patterson, Henry (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Payton, Carolyn (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Peterson, Lizette (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Peterson, Mary (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Placone, Richard (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Plenum Pub. Co. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Polak, Paul (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Protsik, Ralph (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Psych. Comm. Proj. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Public Advocates (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - R (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - S (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - T (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Talpers, Jeanne (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - U (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - V (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - W (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - XYZ (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence Prior to 1974 (1 of 7) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence Prior to 1974 (2 of 7) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence Prior to 1974 (3 of 7) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence Prior to 1974 (4 of 7) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence Prior to 1974 (5 of 7) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence Prior to 1974 (6 of 7) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence Prior to 1974 (7 of 7) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - R (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - S (Box 1, Folder 17)